Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
Flowing Away
（柳原(やなぎはら)･島田(しまだ)）ンン〜ッ…
Master Souya Touji
The challenge to
a beautiful future
2008 Rookie King
Kiriyama Rei, 5-dan
The 43rd Rookie Tournament
Commemorative Match
What is this?
（島田）なに？　これ
なに？　このポスター
What is this poster?
What is this?
（柳原）なに？　これ
デザイン 超カッコイイんですけど
Why is the design so cool?
（島田）すげえいい紙で—
It's on really nice paper,
and it looks like the letters are popping off the page.
しかも 文字とか
浮き上がって見えるんですけど
（柳原）ただの新人王と名人との
記念対局だよね？
It's just a commemorative battle between the Rookie King and a Master, right?
Parts of it have like a matte finish and other parts of it are shiny...
（島田）なんか マットな所と
光ってる所がありますよね
A special manufacturing process?
特殊加工？
What is this?
（柳原）なに？　これ
Why are they making incredible posters like these?
こんな すっごいポスター
作っちゃってんの？
Jab
（神宮寺(じんぐうじ)）
よっ！　気づいちゃった？
Jab
Yo!
Did you notice?
Cool, right?
カッコイイっしょ？
（指を鳴らす音）
You guys have some expert eyes.
さすが お目が高い！
I hired a designer to do it!
デザイナーさんに頼んじゃったのよ
“カッコよくしてね”って
I told him to make it cool.
I even splurged on the printing.
印刷も ちょびっと奮発しちゃった
I don't want to hear it, Toku!
そんなこと言ってんじゃないよ
徳(とく)ちゃん！
I mean, our posters look like that!
だって
俺たちのポスター こんなだぜ
33rd Shogi Maestro Championship
Shogi Maestro
Yanagihara Sakutarou
Shimada Kai, 8-dan
Only necessary
information
included
Only necessary
information
included
Plain
When was that photo taken?
（柳原）これ いつの写真よ？
何のときの写真の使い回しよ？
What occasion was it originally used for?
The picture is kind of grainy!
粒子 微妙に粗いんですけど
Tell me!
Nervous
ねえ？
And... how can I put this?
あと 何て言ったらいいのかな
This poster wasn't professionally printed, but made by the association, wasn't it?
これ 多分 印刷じゃなくて
連盟で出力したやつですよね？
Nervous
ただの…
And not only that, and I'm not sure how to put this,
the photo of the hotel venue is strangely—
しかも 何ていうか
会場のホテルの写真が微妙に…
no, definitely way bigger than we are!
ていうか あからさまに
でっかいんですけど！
That's awful!
Eeeek
ひどいよ！
桐山(きりやま)と宗谷(そうや)が ちいっとばかり
若くて かわいいからって—
How can you treat us like this just because
Kiriyama and Souya are a bit younger and cuter?!
なに？　この扱い
My Eternal Shogi Maestro title is on the line!
俺 棋匠戦(きしょうせん)
永世かかってるんですけど
Eter
nal
あと 心なしか ポスターのサイズも
小さいんですけど！
Not to mention, that poster is kind of small!
What do you want me to do?!
しかたないだろうが！
We're in a recession and barely scraping by because of lack of sponsors!
今 不景気でスポンサーつかなくて
こっちだってカツカツなんだよ！
And besides, what was that first match?
大体 何よ？　あの１局目
Fans won't come, and the players' match is as shaky as their broken-down bodies!
客は来ねえわ
体調と内容はガタガタだわ
Can't say anything back...
Video replay
（柳原の せきこみ）
Old man, one step
away from pneumonia
Creak
Chronic gastritis
(about to become a stomach ulcer)
Creak
Cough
Hack
Ahem
Choke
the sickly   showdown
Cough
Ahem
Choke
（神宮寺）なに？　あの病人対局
あんたら 体弱すぎだろう！
What was that match between two invalids?
Cough
Choke
Ahem
Cough
Your bodies are too weak!
Choke
Cough
Ahem
On top of that, it was an unsightly psychological battle.
その上 更に 醜い心理合戦
し… 島田　玉頭(ぎょくとう) 薄くない？
Sh-Shimada, is the head of your king looking a bit thin?
Your king.
玉頭が…　玉の頭が薄くない？
It isn't getting a bit thin on top?
Creak
It is not thin.
薄くないですよ
…ていうか わざとですから
Creak
That's how I like it.
What was that?! What kind of battle?!
なに？　あれ　どんな修羅場よ？
Full of coughing and grinding teeth and abusive language!
せきと歯ぎしりと悪態と
In recent years, playing quietly was the norm!
近年はね 静かに指すのが普通なの
When is your shogi from? The Showa period?
いつの将棋よ？　昭和(しょうわ)？
君ら 昭和のままなの？
Are you guys from the 80s?!
Whisper
People watching the stream were having a blast, though.
（重田(しげた)）ネット中継じゃ
超盛り上がったんだけどな
Demo board commentator
（横溝(よこみぞ)）うん
Video replay
（横溝）現場は
アットホームな感じで
It was an "at-home" feel with not many people, so that actually made it really exciting.
実は 超盛り上がったん
ですけどね
少人数で
Whoa! Shimada, 8-dan, moves his silver from 4b to 5a.
（横溝）
おっと 島田八段
ここで５一銀左
Online
Shogi Maestro Championship
Second Match
えっ？　５一銀左？
Huh?
From 4b to 5a?
What?!
Double
take
Shogi Maestro Championship
Second Match
Silver from 4b to 5a?
５一銀左って これは ないでしょう
Why would he do that?
Just between you and me,
I have a feeling that's going to cost him the match.
ここだけの話 むっちゃ
敗着の香りがするんですけど
Seriously?
マジでか？　５一銀左？
Silver from 4b to 5a?
Oh yeah! That's no good!
*Apparently there are so few people in the demo
board room that everyone's formed a circle...
（男性）ホントだ　ダメじゃん
（男性）ダメですよね？　これ
That is a lousy move, isn't it?
Ugh!
フヘ〜ッ！
If you don't like it, then get your health back, and some sponsors too while you're at it!
悔しかったら健康を取り戻して
スポンサーも取ってくるこったな！
Sponsors: Morisen Publishing, Morioka Bookstore, Hanamaki Electronics, Etc.
Ba-bam
Look at this! See how popular Souya and Kiriyama are?
見てよ 宗谷と桐山を
この人気っぷりを！
Damn it, Shimada! It's your fault!
（柳原）
くそ…　島田　お前のせいだぞ！
If Gakuto were the challenger,
this place would be packed with female fans!
挑戦者が岳人(がくと)だったら 女性客とか
ガッツリ取り込めたのに！
（櫻井(さくらい)）オッ…
ハハッ…　お待ちしています
I'll be waiting for you.
Shogi Maestro Tournament spectator bus tour,
including a lunch party with both players
It's my fault?
俺のせい？　ええっ？
What?
Shogi
Hall
True, we both have lousy health,
and that match was somewhat appalling,
（柳原）確かに 体調はボロクソで
内容だって—
確かに ありえんくらいの
ひどさだったがな
but however you get there, a win is a win.
どんな勝負だろうと勝ちは勝ちだ
And I won!
俺のな！
Not only that...
そして 次も絶対に勝つよ
I'm going to win the next one too.
I won't let anyone take the Shogi Maestro title away from me.
棋匠のタイトルだけは誰にも譲らん
俺の命だ！
It's my life!
あっ…　柳原さん…
Yanagihara.
Souya is putting everything into the Master Tournament, so the other tournaments become empty.
宗谷が名人戦に全力を傾けて—
ほかが お留守になる
唯一の このタイトルだけはな
This is the one title I'm hanging on to, even if it kills me!
死んでも離さん！
さらばだ 諸君　ヌハハハハッ…
Farewell, gentlemen!
What?!
ええっ!?　正直にも程のある発言
You didn't have to be that blunt!
Go home, get a good night's sleep, and let your body rest!
さっさと帰って
早く寝て 体 休めてくださいよ！
I can't believe I wasted my time thinking you were cool!
カッコイイとか思って損したよ！
Well, you two can keep going at it like that.
（神宮寺）まあ 君たちは
そうやって争い続けるがいいさ
Souya and
Kiriyama posters
I'm going to get people psyched for this
high-profile match, Souya versus Kiriyama.
こっちは
この話題のカード
宗谷ＶＳ桐山で—
盛り上がらせて
いただくからな
Hahaha!
Still, Chairman,
でも 会長
please go easy on them.
ちょっと
手加減してやってくださいね
I don't think either of them are comfortable being the center of attention.
宗谷も桐山も
矢面とか そういうの—
やっぱり苦手だと思うんで
I know.
分かってるよ
俺だって 宗谷とは長いつきあいだ
I've known Souya for a long time too,
so I know that about him.
その辺は分かってる
I'm not going to kill the golden goose.
金のガチョウの
腹割くようなマネは しねえよ
そうか　桐山
I see.
Kiriyama...
いよいよ当たるんだな 宗谷に
So you're facing Souya...
at last.
Hey, Kiriyama.
（林田(はやしだ)）おう 桐山　いたいた
There you are.
（林田）すっげえ集中力
全然 聞こえてないな
What incredible concentration.
He can't even hear me.
（零(れい)）ウワッ！
大事な棋譜に！　キャ〜ッ！
The precious match record!
Hey, Kiriyama.
（林田）よう 桐山…
（零）ンンッ…　あっ 先生
Oh, Mr. Hayashida.
That commemorative match is in Morioka, right?
（林田）記念対局 盛岡(もりおか)だっけ？
用意できた？
Are you ready for it?
Yes.
（零）
はい　準備とかは特にないですし
There's really nothing to prepare for.
Are you going to wear a kimono?
（林田）着物とか着るのか？
No, the chairman said my school uniform was okay.
（零）
あっ いえ　制服でいいって会長が
ハァ〜ッ…　緊張してっか？
Are you nervous?
あっ…　はい
Yes.
But for some reason, it doesn't feel real to me.
でも なんだか
現実感が湧かなくって
あっ…　そうだ 先生
Oh, that's right! Mr. Hayashida...
（林田）そうか　解決したのか
I see.
So it's been resolved.
（零）はい
Yes.
It's like the air around her is totally different.
なんか こう…
空気が もう全然 違うんです
なんか
フワフワッとしてるっていうか
Kind of like a light, airy feeling.
She said there's nothing to worry about anymore.
（零）
もう何も緊張しなくていいって…
こんなにも力が抜けて
柔らかくなれるんだって
She's let all of her muscles relax and can just rest easy.
It makes me think about just how much she suffered all that time.
ホントに どんなにか ずっとずっと
つらかったことだろうって…
That's great, Kiriyama.
良かったな 桐山
No, Mr. Hayashida...
（零）いや 先生
I...
僕は 結局 現実には
何の役にも立てませんでした
In the end, I wasn't any help at all.
それ 彼女に言ったか？
Did you tell her that?
えっ？　あっ…　はい
Yes.
And what did she say?
（林田）彼女 何て答えた？
（零）えっ？　あの…
What?
Um...
She said, "That's not true," didn't she?
（林田）
そんなことないって言われたろう？
あっ…　はい
Yes.
Huh? How did you know?
えっ？　でも 先生　なんで？
分かるよ んなもん
ずっと話聞いてきたんだからさ
It's easy to figure out.
I've been listening to you this whole time.
So I know you were doing everything you could to help her
お前が
どれだけ一生懸命だったかも—
彼女が どんなに—
and that she's a girl with a good head on her
shoulders who has a good sense of the world.
いろんなこと分かってしまう
ちゃんとした子だとかもな
Results are important, but it's not results that reach people.
結果は大事だけどな　桐山
人に伝わるのは結果だけじゃない
The world doesn't revolve around results.
世界は 結果だけで
回ってるんじゃないんだよ
Good luck with the commemorative match.
記念対局 頑張れよ
（零）はい
Thank you.
I had to attend a reception on the eve of the match,
（零）
そして 前夜祭に出席するため—
so I met up with people from newspapers and the association that afternoon.
対局の前日
新聞社や連盟の人と合流して…
We took a bullet train there.
新幹線に乗り込んだ
Master Souya was sitting a few seats away from me.
少し離れた席に
宗谷名人が座っていた
His profile was a face with closed eyes.
目を閉じた彼の横顔
そこだけが まるで…
No sound came from it,
just like the bottom of a lake.
湖の底みたいに音がなかった
Stillness and a violent storm...
静けさと激しい嵐と
これが 僕の—
That was the beginning of four days I never could've imagined.
あの想像もつかなかった４日間の
始まりだった
Flowing Away
White Storm (Part 1)
（零）う… うわぁ…
（零）ほえ〜…
お… 思ってたより ずっと—
I-It's a much bigger hotel than I'd pictured.
で… でっかいホテルだよ
Welcome
Rookie Tournament
Commemorative Match
All lined up
Welcome!
Master Souya Touji
Kiriyama Rei, 5-dan
Welcome
Rookie Tournament
Commemorative Match
（仲居たち）
ようこそ いらっしゃいませ
Master Souya Touji
Kiriyama Rei, 5-dan
Hi!
は〜い！
どうも どうも　お世話になるよ
Master Souya Touji
Kiriyama Rei, 5-dan
Thanks. I appreciate the hospitality.
（ポーター）お待ちしておりました
どうぞ　お荷物お持ちいたします
We've been waiting for you.
Here, let me take your bag.
Great.
はい　これが
今回の主役のひとり 桐山五段です
This is one of the stars of the show, Kiriyama, 5-dan.
Take care of him!
（神宮寺）よろしくね
（零）ウッ…
Ba-baam
（零）アア…
（神宮寺）さてと　じゃ まず—
Well then, why don't we go to our rooms first?
お部屋に通してもらおっかね
ギャーッ！　なに これ!?
What is this?!
Gosho Lake
This is your room, Kiriyama.
（神宮寺）はい　桐山ちゃんの部屋
Spacious
Isn't the Gosho Lake pretty?
きれいだね 御所湖(ごしょこ)が
Well, you've got some free time until the reception at 7 o'clock.
さあ　あとは前夜祭の始まる
７時までフリータイム
Slap
So relax!
ゆっくりしちゃってよ！
Sho
Shove
ウワッ！
Ba-baaam
All of the baths run from a hot spring source,
but we're going to take a dip in the hot spring itself.
風呂は全て源泉かけ流し
まあ 俺たちは まず
ひとっ風呂 浴びてきちゃうから
Want to come with, Kiriyama?
桐山ちゃんも どう？　一緒に
Also, take this.
あと これ　前夜祭の式次第
軽〜く目を通しといて
It's the program for tonight's reception.
Take a glance at it.
Well, let's meet in the lobby at 6 o'clock.
んじゃ ６時にロビーにな
Umino Egg
Alone...
Glance
The room is so spacious, fancy, and quiet that he can't relax...
温泉…　温泉…
Hot spring...
Hot spring?
A hot spring, huh?
温泉か…　あ〜…
Come to think of it, I guess I've never been in one.
そういえば まだ
入ったことない …かも
Silence
Modern kid
( has never been in a
bath with someone else)
Modern kid
( has never been in a
bath with someone else)
Doesn't have
the courage
to go to the
bigger baths
with everyone
Doesn't have
the courage
to go to the
bigger baths
with everyone
え〜っと…　式次第
Um, the program...
First, the chairman greets everyone.
まず 会長の挨拶に
花束贈呈　来賓挨拶
Then the flower presentation,
guests' address, sponsor speeches,
スポンサーさま スピーチ
主催新聞社会長による乾杯
a toast from the president of the sponsoring newspaper...
Huh?
Players' address,
対局者挨拶
対局者への質問コーナー
Q&A session with the players,
photo session with the players,
対局者撮影会
両対局者 揮毫(きごう)
players' signing...
The reception that night was a lavish affair,
（零）
その夜の前夜祭は盛大なもので
Welcome to the Rookie Tournament Commemorative Match Reception
Master Souya Touji and Kiriyama Rei, 5-dan
たくさんの人で あふれ
overflowing with people,
with lots of flash bulbs going off,
たくさんのフラッシュの中…
（来賓）ここ 岩手は…
（零）たくさんのスピーチが続いた
and lots of speeches being made.
I see.
なるほど
It takes a lot of stamina and willpower to make it through these things.
これは かなりの
体力と気力を必要とする
I've been bowing so much that I feel dizzy.
おじぎのしすぎで
頭がクラクラしてくる
I can't think of anything to say.
言葉が なかなか出てこない
Is this kind of thing run-of-the-mill for him?
あの人は これが日常なのか
Has he been standing alone in this world all this time?
ずっとずっと この世界に
１人で立っているのか？
When he's surrounded by all of these
unfamiliar people and steeling himself,
（二海堂(にかいどう)）大勢の慣れない人に—
周りを囲まれて 気を張って
対局前日に—
I want to support him so he's not worn out before the first match.
疲れちゃわないように
そばにいたいんだ
（拍手）
（零）二海堂
Nikaidou...
You always had an idea of what was going on.
お前は いつだって ちゃんと
いろんなものを見てたんだよな
More than me, anyway.
俺なんかより
Don't try to act cool, Kiriyama!
（二海堂）カッコつけんな 桐山！
NHK Cup
Tournament
If you really want to win, then persevere!
本当に勝ちたいんなら粘れ！
Take better care of your shogi, and yourself!
もっと自分の将棋を…
自分を大切にしてくれ！
If he hadn't said that to me,
I'm sure I wouldn't be standing here right now.
（零）あのひと言がなかったら—
きっと今
ここに立ててはいなかった
Standing next to him.
この人の横には
I wanted to find out what lies on the other side of the storm,
（零）嵐の向こうにあるものを
尋ねてみたいと思ったけれど—
but I realized how unprepared I was to
ask that question when I saw his profile.
それが どんなに
覚悟のない問いであったかは—
あの横顔を見たとき
突き刺さるように分かった
そして 自分が まだ…
And I also realized
嵐の中に
入ってさえもなかったことも
that I'd never even entered a storm before.
This is your first match with Master Souya, isn't it?
（アナウンサー）
宗谷名人とは初対局ですね
How do you feel?
今の気持ちを…
どんな戦いにしたいですか？
How would you like the match to play out?
アア…　えっと…
Um...
The expressions "it's an honor" and
"I'll return blow for blow" popped into my head,
（零）“胸を借りる”とか
“一矢(いっし)報いる”とか—
そんな言葉が浮かんだが—
but what I understood wasn't that, so I couldn't speak properly.
そんなの 全然
違うということだけは分かって—
言葉に詰まった
きっと距離感をつかむだけでも
実際に対局して 数回はかかる
It would take playing against him several times
before I could get a sense of the distance between us.
That's how far away he was.
そのくらい遠い
I-I want to concentrate as I play so the match isn't over as soon as it's begun.
あ… あっという間に
終わってしまわないように—
集中して指したい …です
（アナウンサー）次は宗谷名人
桐山五段について 何か ひと言
The next question is for Master Souya.
Could you say a few words about Kiriyama, 5-dan?
（宗谷）
新人戦の棋譜を見ましたが—
I saw his match records from the Rookie Tournament, and I could tell he's really studying hard.
ものすごく勉強しているなと
思いました
I like how he has a flexible playing style no matter the situation.
それでも硬くなっていないところが
いいと思います
How do you think the match will go tomorrow?
（アナウンサー）あしたは
どんな対局になると思いますか？
This will be our first match together,
so I'd like to see what kind of atmosphere we can create.
初対局なので どんな流れを
作れるかが こちらも楽しみです
H-He's so good at this.
（零）さ… さすがだ
Ah, yes, yes.
Glow
Well said, Master Souya. You've got a way with words.
さすが宗谷名人
いいこと おっしゃる
You've been participating in title matches all year,
so how are you holding up physically?
宗谷名人は １年間
タイトル戦に出ずっぱりですが—
体調などは いかがですか？
I've been coming to Iwate for a number of title matches,
岩手にはタイトル戦で もう何度も
おジャマしているのですが—
いつか
対局以外でも訪れてみたいです
but I'd also like to visit someday without playing a match.
（零）そ… 宗谷名人
天然なのだろうか…
C-Could he be out of it?
あっ…　質問と答えが
かみ合ってないような…
I don't think that answer really matches the question...
U-Um...
あっ え〜っと…
では もうひとつ…
Okay, one more.
All right, thank you.
はい ありがとうございます
Excuse me.
では
I-I'm sorry!
（レセプタント）す… すみません
大変！　お召し物が…
Oh no! Your suit!
Master Souya, are you all right?
（アナウンサー）
宗谷名人　大丈夫ですか？
Souya, um, your clothes...
宗谷さん　あの…　服が…
Yes.
（宗谷）はい
あしたは盛岡の皆さんが
たくさん来てくださると思うので
I believe many people from here
in Morioka will come tomorrow,
楽しんでいただけるよう
桐山五段と一緒に—
so I would like to do my best to have a great match with Kiriyama, 5-dan, that everyone will enjoy.
充実した対局になるように
頑張りたいと思います
（零）
その場にいた誰もが息をのんだ
Everyone in the room held their breath.
No matter how different someone is,
たとえ どんなに異質でも
強ければ それが正道
if they can back it up with results, their methods are justified.
あっ…　何やってんだ 宗谷
えっ？　赤ワインまみれ？
What are you doing, Souya?
What? Drenched in red wine?
I take my eyes off of you for one minute!
ちょっと目を離すと すぐ これだよ
このぼんやり大将！
You absent-minded general!
Come with me! You need to get that off!
ちょっと来い！　早く それ脱げ
あした 対局 どうすんだよ？
What are you going to do for the match tomorrow?
That's the only suit you brought, right?
スーツ それだけだろう？
持ってきたの　…たく もう
Sheesh!
（コンシェルジュ）
赤ワインですか…　う〜ん…
Red wine?
今すぐ シミ抜きにかけてみますが
落ちるかどうか…
I'll do what I can with the stain right away, but I don't know if it'll come out.
うん？　宗谷　シャツと
ネクタイにも飛んでんじゃん
Souya, it's on your shirt and tie too!
（零）彼が去ったあと 皆が
詰めていた息を 一斉に吐き出した
After he left, everyone finally let out their breath.
And then someone muttered a few words.
そして 誰かがポツリと言う
That's a shogi demon.
（来場者）あれは もう将棋の鬼だ
He's barely holding on to his human form.
ギリギリ 人の姿を保ってるだけの
Then, the morning of the match came.
そして 対局の朝が来た
（記者Ａ）あっ 宗谷名人
（記者Ｂ）あれ…　和服だ
Master Souya!
Huh? Traditional Japanese clothes...
（零）その日の朝
That morning,
季節外れの台風が
奄美大島(あまみおおしま)沖から鹿児島に上陸
an out-of-season typhoon went from the sea around Amami Ooshima and made landfall in Kagoshima.
そして その台風は ゆっくりと—
And then,
the news said that the typhoon was slowly moving north,
as if it was licking the Japanese archipelago.
なめるように
日本列島を北上しつつあると—
ニュースが伝えた
White Storm (Part 1)
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
Next Episode Preview
Episode 37
（島田）鳥に似てる
He reminds me of a bird.
Right now,
（零）今から僕は—
I have to cross paths with this person.
この人と渡り合わねば
ならないのだ
A white bird with huge wings.
大きな翼の… 白い鳥
Let's have a good match.
お願いします
Illustration: Hara Tetsuo
（柳原）徳ちゃん
俺もポスター用に—
Toku, I'll take another picture
you can use for a poster,
写真 撮り直すからさ
so next time make me look cool, okay?
次は カッコイイのを
お願いね！